Guide to the Dudley Fitts Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dudley Fitts papers
1928-1968
1941-1943
YCAL MSS 296
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
10.47
(18 boxes)
The Dudley Fitts Papers consists chiefly of writings and correspondence relating to the production of the first American edition of An Anthology of Contemporary Latin-American Poetry (New Directions, 1942).
Fitts, Dudley, 1903-1968
Fitzgerald, Robert, 1910-1985
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Dudley Fitts Papers was aquired through gifts from Dudley and Cornelia Fitts from 1941 to 1969.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile papers in boxes 17-18 may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm available through Access Services.
Dudley Fitts (1903-1968)
Dudley Fitts was a poet, translator, literary critic, and educator. Fitts was perhaps best known for his translations of classical texts. He translated several works by Aristophanes, including Lysistrata (1954), The Frogs (1955), The Birds (1957), and Ladies' Day (1959) and, in collaboration with Robert Fitzgerald, he translated Euripides' The Alcestis (1936) and Sophocles' Antigone (1939) and Oedipus Rex (1949). He is also the author of Poems, 1929-1936 (1937) and editor of An Anthology of Contemporary Latin-American Poetry (1942).
Fitts was born April 28, 1903, in Boston and educated at Harvard. He taught at the Choate School from 1927 to 1941 and then served as an instructor of English at Phillips Academy from 1941 onward.
Scope and Contents
The Dudley Fitts Papers consist chiefly of material relating to the production of the first American edition of An Anthology of Contemporary Latin-American Poetry (New Directions, 1942). Fitts served as editor for Spanish poetry in the bilingual anthology, selecting material and translators, and supervising and editing translations. The papers include both correspondence and writings, the bulk of which date from 1941 to 1943. There are letters with contributing authors and translators, representatives of the sponsoring agency, the Committee on Publications of the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, and the publisher. The writings include typescript copies of poems, drafts of translations, many of which are corrected and annotated, proofs, and other materials.
In addition to the material relating to the anthology, there are letters from other writers, concerning literary matters, and drafts and proofs to translations by Fitts of several classical texts.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1928-1968. II. Writings, 1935-1967.
Editors -- United States -- 20th Century -- Archives; English literature -- 20th Century -- Translations from Spanish; Latin American literature -- 20th Century -- Translations into English; Translators; Aristophanes, 449-; Euripides ( Alcestis); Sophocles, 495-; Carrión, Alejandro; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965; Fitts, Dudley, 1903-1968; Fitzgerald, Robert, 1910-1985; Florit, Eugenio, 1903-1999; Guillén, Jorge, 1893-1984; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Izaguirre, Carlos; Lara, Jesús, 1898-1980; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955; Maugham, W. Somerset (William Somerset), 1874-1965; Méndez Dorich, Rafael; Mizener, Arthur, 1907-; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972; Rokha, Pablo de, 1894-1968; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946; United States. Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs; New Directions Publishing Corp
- Correspondence, 1928-1968; Series I; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence consists chiefly of letters relating to the first American edition of An Anthology of Contemporary Latin-American Poetry (New Directions, 1942). Fitts served as editor for Spanish poetry in the bilingual anthology, selecting material and translators, and supervising and editing translations. There are both original incoming letters and carbon copies of outgoing letters, dating from 1941 to 1943, with contributing authors and translators, representatives of the sponsoring agency, the Committee on Publications of the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, and the publisher. Contributing authors include Jorge Carrera Andrade, Alejandro Carrión, Eugenio Florit, Carlos Izaguirre, Jesús Lara, Rafael Méndez Dorich, Hipólito Quell Sánchez, and others. Translators include Angel Flores, Joseph Leonard Grucci, H. R. Hays, Langston Hughes, Rolfe Humphries, Muna Lee, Lloyd Mallan, Richard O'Connell, Donald Walsh, and others. Correspondence with authors and translators concern submissions, and some include copies of original poems, drafts of translations, and lists of corrections. Correspondence with Robert S. Benjamin, John Peale Bishop, Dudley Poore, and other members of the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs documents production of the anthology.
  Other noteworthy correspondents include T. S. Eliot, Archibald MacLeish, Thomas Mann, William Somerset Maugham, Ezra Pound, and Gertrude Stein.
  Correspondence is in English and Spanish.
  - Abril, Xavier, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Acero, Julio, 1943 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arrom, José Juan, 1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Asociación de Escritores y Artistas Americanos, 1943 January 13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Asturias, Miguel Angel, 1943 June (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beilenson, Peter, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Benét, William Rose, 1952 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Benjamin, Robert S.
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: United States. Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, Box 2, folders 63-69
  - Bishop, John Peale
  - Cadilla, Carmen Alicia, 1943 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Carrera Andrade, Jorge, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carrión, Alejandro, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Casa de la Cultura Ecuatoriana, 1945 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Castro, Oscar, 1942 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chapin, Katherine Garrision, 1946 March 19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Davis, Milton B., 1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Diaz Casanueva, Humberto, 1941 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1928-1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Figueira, Gastón, 1943 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Flores, Angel, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Florit, Eugenio, 1943-1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Girondo, Oliverio, 1943 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - González, Martìnez, Enrique, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Grierson, Herbert John Clifford, Sir, 1942 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Grucci, Joseph Leonard, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Guillén, Jorge, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hays, H. R. (Hoffman Reynolds), 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Heredia, José Ramón, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hespelt, E. Herman (Ernest Herman), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - How, Louis, 1941 July (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Hughes, Langston, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Huidobro, Vincente, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Humphries, Rolfe, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Izaguirre, Carlos, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1943 February (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Lara, Jesús, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Laughlin, James, 1941-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Lee, Muna, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Lieber, Maxim, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Lopez Castellón, Blanca, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Mallan, Lloyd, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Mann, Thomas, 1952 January (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Maugham, W. Somerset (William Somerset), 1943 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Méndez Dorich, Rafael, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Mizener, Rosemary, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    General note
    Includes poem entitled ""Metathalmion"
  - Neruda, Pablo, 1942 February 8 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - New Directions
    See: Laughlin, James, Box 1, folder 35
  - Obaldìa, Maria Olimpia de, 1943 April 15 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Ocampo, Silvina, 1946 February (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - O'Connell, Richard, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Ortiz de Montellano, B., 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Pan American Union, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Pedroso, Regina, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Peralta, Alejandro, 1944 July10 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Poore, Dudley
  - Pound, Ezra, 1931-1949 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Reyes, Alfonso, 1943 April 14 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Rokha, Pablo de, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Romero James, Concha, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Salazar Mallén, Rubén, 1946 March 21 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Sánchez Quell, Hipólito, 1943 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - South African Broadcasting Corporation, 1948 June 9 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Stein, Gertrude, 1935 February 2 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Toklas, Alice B., 1935 [August 1?] (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - United States. Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, 1941-1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 63-69)
    Includes third-party correspondence
  - Valle, Rafael Heliodoro, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Vásquez, Emilio, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Vaval, Duraciné, 1943 May 5 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Walsh, Donald Devenish, 1941-1946, undated (Box 3, Folder 73-76)
  - Westphalen, [Emilio Adolfo?], 1941 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Wicker, C. V. (Cecil Vivian), 1941 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Yale University. Library, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - General correspondence, 1941-1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
    Includes carbons of outgoing correspondence to José Antonio Dávila, Pablo Neruda, Jacques Roumain, and others
- Writings, 1935-1967; Series II; 3.13; (8 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Writings consist chiefly of material relating to the first American edition of An Anthology of Contemporary Latin-American Poetry (New Directions, 1942). Fitts served as editor for Spanish poetry in the bilingual anthology, selecting material and translators, and supervising and editing translations. Materials include typescript copies of poems, drafts of translations, many of which are corrected and annotated, proofs, and other materials. Copies of poems and drafts of translations, housed in boxes 4-7, are arranged alphabetically by author.
  In addition to the material relating to An Anthology of Contemporary Latin-American Poetry, there are drafts, proofs, and other materials relating to several translations by Fitts. These translations, some done in collaboration with Robert Fitzgerald, include texts by Aristophanes ( Lysistrata, The Frogs, The Birds, and Ladies' Day ), Euripides ( The Alcestis ), and Sophocles ( Antigone and Oedipus Rex ).
  - An Anthology of Contemporary Latin-American Poetry
    - Lists of authors, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Research materials, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Copies of poems and drafts of translations, [1941-1942] (Box 4, Folder 83-115)
    - Copies of poems and drafts of translations, [1941-1942] (Box 5, Folder 116-147)
    - Copies of poems and drafts of translations, [1941-1942] (Box 6, Folder 148-177)
    - Copies of poems and drafts of translations, [1941-1942] (Box 7, Folder 178-193)
    - Table of contents, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 194)
    - Notes, drafts and page proofs for preface, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 195-196)
    - Drafts for Biographical and Bibliographical Notes by H. R. Hays, undated (Box 8, Folder 197-200)
    - Comments on Notes by Muna Lee, undated (Box 8, Folder 201)
    - Page proofs for Biographical and Bibliographical Notes by H. R. Hays, undated (Box 8, Folder 202)
    - Galley proofs, [1942?] (Box 8, Folder 203)
      Also stored in: Oversize, Box 12, folders 237-253
    - Page proofs, undated (Box 8, Folder 204-207)
    - Page proofs, undated (Box 9, Folder 208-209)
    - Printed ephemera, 1942-1943, undated (Box 9, Folder 210)
      Also stored in: Oversize, Box 12, folder 254
    - Financial records, 1946, undated (Box 9, Folder 211)
  - Alcestis
    - Drafts, 1935, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 212-213)
  - Antigone
    - Drafts, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 214-215)
    - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 216)
  - The Birds
    - Setting copy, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 217)
    - Galley proofs, undated
      Stored in: Oversize, Boxes 13-14, folders 255-256
    - Page proofs, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 218)
      Also stored in: Oversize, Boxes 15-16, folders 257-258
  - La Comédie de Maître Mimin
    - Draft, 1936 October (Box 10, Folder 219)
  - "Five Poems" by Rafael Alberti
    - Drafts, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 220)
  - The Frogs
    - Draft, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 221)
  - Ladies' Day
    - Drafts, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 222-223)
  - Lysistrata
    - Draft, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 224-225)
    - Music for Lysistrata by Thomas Eastwood, undated (Box 11, Folder 226)
  - Oedipus Rex
    - Draft, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 227-230)
    - Galley proof of index and notes, undated (Box 11, Folder 231)
    - Script for BBC version, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 232)
  - Sixty Poems of Martial
    - Drafts, 1954, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 233-234)
    - Setting typescript, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 235)
    - Page proofs, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 236)
- Oversize, 1942-1957; 5.67; (5 boxes)
  - Galley proofs of An Anthology of Contemporary Latin-American Poetry (In Series II), [1942?] (Box 12, Folder 237-253)
  - Printed ephemera (In Series II), 1943 (Box 12, Folder 254)
  - Galley proof of The Birds (In Series II), 1957 (Box 13, Folder 255)
  - Galley proof of The Birds (In Series II), 1957 (Box 14, Folder 256)
  - Page proof of The Birds (In Series II), 1957 (Box 15, Folder 257)
  - Page proof of The Birds (In Series II), 1957 (Box 16, Folder 258)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 17-18: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Correspondence (In Series I) (Box 17, Folder 259-282)
    Box 17: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Writings (In Series II) (Box 17, Folder 283-334)
  - Writings (In Series II) (Box 18, Folder 335-356)
    Box 18: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.